Functional Requirements

1.4

Support for effective and flexible production of braille on paper/embosser files

4.1:25 The system shall support editing on block level in order to fix wrong translations, e.g. in the case of complex material such as mathematics. It is assumed that all other improvements outside blocks can be accomplished by changing the input document.

4.1:26 The system shall support editing beyond block level, e.g. in order to change the layout of tables or to manually alter the volume breaking.

4.1:27 The system shall be able to merge changes made in the original text with changes made previously in the braille version (possibly independently by another person). This ensures that the transcriber is not condemned to keeping on editing in the braille version after the smallest change.

4.1:28 The system shall be able to produce “synchronization data” for various intermediary and output files, which can be used for finding a location in one file that corresponds to a location in another file.

4.1:29 The system shall provide a graphical user interface for editing an intermediary braille file.

4.1:30 The user interface shall provide a side-by-side view of the original text and braille with synchronized cursor positions. For any position in the braille view, the user shall instantly see the corresponding original text, so that he/she is encouraged to do changes in the original whenever possible.

4.1:31 There shall be support for inserting braille characters using 6/8 keys on the keyboard.

Support for effective and flexible production of braille in electronic form

4.2:32 The system shall be able to output various e-braille formats.

4.2:33 The system shall support a new e-braille format.

Support for languages used in the countries of the interested parties

4.3:34
4.3:34C The system shall support the braille code used in Denmark, Finland, Norway, Sweden and Switzerland for uncontracted braille.
The system shall support the braille code used in the Netherlands for uncontracted braille.

Examples:

Finnish (external Liblouis harness test)
Swedish (tested with Dotify)
Swedish (tested with Liblouis)
Norwegian (external Liblouis harness test)
Dutch (external Liblouis harness test)

4.3:34B The system shall be easily extended with new languages - for uncontracted braille - to make the system work globally in the long term.

4.3:35
4.3:35B The system shall support the braille code used in Denmark, Finland, Norway, Sweden and Switzerland for 8-dot braille.
The system shall support the braille code used in the Netherlands for 8-dot braille.

4.3:35C The system shall support the possibility to leave out capital signs in some products.

4.3:36 The system shall support double letter spacing, meaning adding a space between characters. Some characters should be kept together such as a capital sign and a letter.

Celia requirements and examples:

There are three subtypes of books with double letter spacing. In the first one, intended for early primary education, the original print text is usually in all caps with no punctuation. The braille has only letter signs, no capital signs. Hyphenation is to be avoided. Between words there are 3 spaces.

In the second type, also intended for early primary education, the print text is pre- hyphenated. The text is capitalized with the usual rules and punctuation is used. In braille, capital sign and number sign are attached to the next character. Numbers don't have spaces in between. Punctuation marks are attached to the previous character, except the hyphen that has a space on both sides. In this regard, the pre-existing hyphen can be considered as an ordinary letter. Between words there are 3 spaces. Breaking words across multiple lines is to be avoided.

In the third type, intended for literate braille learners, the original print text is not pre-hyphenated and punctuation and capitalization are used. In braille, capital and number signs are attached to the next character. Numbers don't have spaces in between. Punctuation marks are attached to the previous character. Hyphenation may be used, if required, to break words across multiple lines. If this happens, the hyphen is attached to the previous character. Between words there are 3 spaces.

Example 1 (type 1, 2 and 3)
Example 2 (type 3)
Example 3 (type 3)
Example 4 (type 3)

4.3:37 The system shall support the braille code used in Denmark, Norway, Sweden and Switzerland for contracted braille.

Examples:

Norwegian grade 1 (external Liblouis harness test)
Norwegian grade 2 (external Liblouis harness test)

4.3:37B The system shall be easily extended with new languages - for contracted braille - to make the system work globally in the long term.

4.3:37C The system shall support the braille code used in the Netherlands for contracted braille.

4.3:38 The system shall support marking of text-level semantics (i.e. em, strong) with braille indicators.

Examples:

Finnish uncontracted
Norwegian

4.3:39 The system shall support marking of visual text styling/typography (i.e. span[@class]) with braille indicators. This is because we are often dealing with input files that are marked up according to visual features of the print text instead of semantic meaning.

4.3:40 The system shall have a flexible and configurable mapping from markup to braille indicators. Because there is only a limited set of braille indicators they must be reused for different semantic meanings or typography depending on document and context. It must be possible to ignore certain styles that don't convey any useful information for the braille version.

4.3:41 The system shall be able to perform automatic hyphenation for uncontracted and contracted braille.

Examples:

Finnish uncontracted (external JUnit test)
Norwegian (line breaking)
Norwegian (single words)
Dutch (single words)

4.3:42 The system shall support non-standard hyphenation. By non-standard hyphenation we mean that the spelling of a word can change when it is hyphenated. The braille translation of a hyphenated word can only change because the spelling changes, not e.g. because it is contracted in some other way. In other words the definition of non-standard hyphenation is not “extrapolated to braille”.

4.3:43 When automatic hyphenation is enabled, it shall be possible to exclude certain elements such as hyperlinks (based on markup).

Example

4.3:44 The user shall be able to make a top-level configuration, e.g. toggle hyphenation.

4.3:45 The user shall have fine-grained control over the translation (on element-level) by means of configuration in those cases where markup of the input is inadequate or undesirable.

Support for layout/formatting of paragraphs/text blocks

4.4:46 The system shall have support for top, right, bottom and left margins on blocks.

Example

4.4:47 The system shall have support for top, right, bottom and left borders and padding on blocks.

Example

SBS examples:

Block start/end indicator lines
Thin left border
Thick left border
Full box

4.4:48 By default margins shall be collapsing. However there shall be a way to override this behaviour.

4.4:49 By default empty lines at the top and bottom of a page shall be suppressed. However there shall be a way to override this behaviour.

4.4:50 There shall be the possibility of shrinking a block with a border to the size of its contents. This feature shall be supported at least for blocks with left-aligned text and no nested blocks.

SBS example

4.4:51 The system shall have support for first line indentation.

4.4:52 Besides left-aligned text, the system shall have support for centered and right-aligned text.

4.4:53 The system shall support block alignment relative to a vertical position on the page.

SBS example: Vertical positioning on title pages.

4.4:54 The system shall by default handle whitespace characters (spaces, tabs, line feeds) in the source XML according to the following rules:

Comments are removed entirely and do not affect whitespace handling.
All whitespace surrounding block elements is removed.
Leading and trailing whitespace inside block elements are removed.
Sequences of whitespace characters are reduced to a single space character. Newline characters are handled as other whitespace.

Example

4.4:55 The user shall be able to override the default handling of whitespace for certain elements:

Prevent collapsing of sequences of whitespace.
Preserve leading and trailing whitespace inside block elements.
Preserve newline characters as forced line breaks.

SBS examples:

Preserve newline characters (br elements) as forced line breaks.
Preserve two spaces before and after mathematical expressions, but not at the beginning or end of a line.

4.4:57 There shall be the option to reformat a table into a list,

either by linearizing the table row-by-row with delimiters between cells,
or by rendering each row as a sublist, where the cells are the list items. It must be possible to set off cells with a left margin according to their column, so that a stairstep format can be accomplished.
It must be possible to prepend cells with their column header.

4.4:58 There shall be the option to render a table in matrix format, thereby mimicking the original form. This feature shall be supported at least for small tables that fit on a page horizontally without the need for text wrapping in cells, and that have no column- or rowspan. The matrix format supports borders and padding on rows, columns and cells.

4.4:56 The system shall provide a way to control the layout of each table separately.

4.4:59 When a table in matrix format spans multiple pages, there shall be the possibility of repeating the table heading at the top of each page.

4.4:60 There shall be the possibility of transposing tables, that is, treat rows as if they were columns and columns as if they were rows.

4.4:61 The system shall provide a table layout fallback mechanism that determines the best way to render a certain table by trying several alternatives.

4.4:62 The system shall be able to cope with column- and rowspan in tables (in a yet undefined way).

4.4:63 There shall be the option to render a big or complex table in matrix format through wrapping of text in cells and automatic computing of optimal column widths.

4.4:64 There shall be the option to render a wide table on facing pages.

4.4:65 The system shall be able to render tables of contents, list of images, index, glossaries, etc. in a two-column format with the entries on the left and other content such as page numbers aligned on the right. Optionally leaders may be used to connect the two columns.

4.4:66 The system shall support positioning of notes at the bottom of the page on which they are being referenced.

4.4:67 The system shall support collecting of notes either at the end of each volume, or at the end of the entire book.

4.4:68 The system shall provide a notes layout fallback mechanism that determines the best way to render notes. Notes of a certain type (e.g. footnote or endnote) shall be handled consistently throughout the whole document.

4.4:69 The system shall support inline rendering of notes right after the note reference, possibly surrounded by brackets or the like. This feature shall be supported at least for very small notes. As an option, notes may be floated to the end of sentences.

4.4:70 The system shall support rendering of certain elements such as line numbers in the left margin, taking them out of the normal text flow so that text that follows the element can continue on the same line.

4.4:71 The system shall provide the possibility of moving certain content that hinders readability, such as large tables, to a later position in the document.

4.4:72 The system shall provide the possibility of omitting certain content.

4.4:73 There shall be the possibility of rendering certain elements such as line numbers in the left margin, thereby reducing the area for normal text. A line break is inserted first whenever such an element is placed in the left margin, text that follows the element starts on the new line as well. In other words, the element is not taken out of the normal flow of the text.

4.4:74 The system shall support single and double line spacing.

NLB examples:

Single line spacing
Double line spacing

It shall be possible to configure line spacing on section level, i.e. to switch from a single line spacing section to a double line spacing section or vice-versa.

MTM example: Single line spacing on title page, double line spacing on subsequent pages.

4.4:75 When printing double-sided with line spacing greater than 1, printed lines shall alternate on odd and even pages.

Optionally the header lines shall overlap.

SBS example: Printed lines alternate on odd and even pages.
MTM example: Printed lines alternate on odd and even pages, header lines overlap.

4.4:76 The system shall support line spacing between single and double.

Support for pagination

4.5:78 The user shall have control over page breaking by means of

inserting hard page breaks,
protecting blocks from being split across multiple pages,
avoiding page breaks within blocks leaving only the first line(s) on the first page (orphan control),
avoiding page breaks within blocks leaving only the last line(s) on the second page (widow control), and
keeping a block’s first line(s) on the same page as the preceding block.

Celia example: Cover pages embossed separately as a 4 page set, text only on the first page.

4.5:79 The system shall provide the option to disable page breaking for the purpose of producing digital documents (for reading on a refreshable braille display).

4.5:80 The user shall have control over the page dimensions and the size of page margins.

SBS examples:

Page width = 28 cells, page height = 28 lines
Page width = 36 cells, page height = 18 lines
Page width = 28 cells, page height = 28 lines, left margin = 2 cells

Celia examples: Top margin of 2 lines.

Example 1
Example 2
Example 3

4.5:81 There shall be support for content in the header and footer of pages. Content can be rendered in the left corner, the center and the right corner.

Nota examples of footer layout1:

Example without indication of print pagination.
Example with indication of print pagination.

Explanation: Footers appear on recto pages only. The footer consists of a single line at the bottom of the page. No text flows into the footer. Generally, the footer contains only the braille page number (right-aligned); however, if indication of print pagination is enabled, the footer will also contain (centered) the print page or range of print pages covered by the current braille page.

SBS examples of various footer layouts:

Braille page number on the right, text flows into the footer. (1)
Braille page number on the right, text flows into the footer. (2)
Braille page number on the right, print page number on the left.
Braille page number on the right, print page number on the left, chapter info (heading) in the middle.
Braille page number on the right, no print page number, chapter info (heading).

Celia examples of various header layouts:

Braille page number in the corner, no text flows in the header.
Braille page number on first row, print page number on second row.
Braille page number on top and the current print page number under it, both without any text flow.
Braille page number on top and beneath it the current print page in brackets with hint word.

4.5:82 The header and footer layout shall be able to change between sections within the document.

SBS example: Footer layout in frontmatter is different from footer layout in bodymatter.

4.5:83 The system shall support flowing of text into the header or footer. With this is meant normal text that wraps around content in the right corner of the header or footer, not text that simply extends to the top or bottom of the page because there is no content in the header/footer. When there is content in either the left corner or the center, flowing into the header/footer is not allowed.

SBS examples: Flowing of text into the footer. At least 4 cells before the braille page number must remain empty.

Example 1
Example 2

Celia examples: Flowing of test into the header.

Text can flow in the header with the page number in the right corner.
Text can flow in the header with page numbers in the top left or top right corner.

4.5:84 When printing double-sided, there shall be support for hard page breaks that jump to the next right- or left-hand page.

MTM example: Jump to first right-hand page after title page.

4.5:85 When printing double-sided, the system shall allow the page layout (page margins as well as header and footer layout) to differ between left- and right-hand pages.

It is assumed that the inner margins of a sheet are always equal on both sides, and similarly the outer margins of a sheet are always equal.

MTM example: Even braille page numbers are on the left, odd braille page numbers on the right.

SBS examples: Footers only appear on right hand pages.

Example 1
Example 2

Celia examples:

Braille page number switches corner between left- and right-hand pages. (1)
Braille page number switches corner between left- and right-hand pages. (2)
Braille page number can change corners but the print page number doesn't have to follow.

Nota examples: Footers appear on recto pages only1.

Example 1
Example 2

4.5:86 Support for mixed braille and ink on the cover page, the main purpose being to help sighted people in finding a specific volume of a specific title. This feature doesn't require the text in ink to be exactly that of the original (so back-translation would be a possibility).

4.5:87 Support for interlining braille and ink, or combining braille and ink on facing pages. This feature requires synchronization between the source and the braille with medium (for facing pages) to high (for interlining) precision.

Support for volume breaking

4.6:88 The system shall be able to perform automatic volume breaking with constraints. It shall be possible to precisely tweak the algorithm. It shall take values for minimal and maximal number of pages per volume. It shall support special ranges for the first and last volume of sections. The algorithm shall take into account that certain points in the book are better suited for being the start of a new volume than other points and that certain sections belong in certain volumes.

4.6:89 The system shall provide the possibility of repeating certain content, such as title pages, in several volumes.

4.6:90 The system shall support trimming down of a table of contents to a volume-scope table of contents that includes only the entries that reference items present in the current volume.

4.6:91 In the case of an extended table of contents that is not trimmed down (e.g. in the first volume), it shall be possible to group entries according to volume and insert a heading before each group.

4.6:92 In the case of endnotes being collected at the end of a book, it shall be possible to group the notes according to volume and insert a heading before each group.

4.6:93 The user shall have some form of manual control over volume breaking.

Support for generated content

4.7:94 The system shall support formatting of numbers and other variables in a wide selection of formats. Supported formats shall include at least arabic, roman (small and capital), alpha (small and capital), downshifted, written out, and various date formats. It shall be possible to specify number prefixes and suffixes too. Some numbers might need specialized translation, such as ranges of print pages.

SBS examples of "downshifted number format":

Example 1
Example 2

4.7:96 The system shall support automatic insertion of content that is not present in the source. Examples include:

boilerplate text inserted e.g. on the title page,
metadata and details about the production process,
automatic transcriber notes that give information about omitted or moved content, about how tables are rendered,
etc.

4.7:95 The system shall support insertion of content that is not present in the source, through configuration. Examples include:

boilerplate text inserted e.g. on the title pages/colophons,
freely definable one-character marks inserted in the left margin at certain elements,
configurable titles for sidebars, figures,
etc.

4.7:97 The system shall be able to perform automatic numbering of braille pages and volumes.

4.7:98 The system shall be able to perform automatic numbering on type "ol" lists. This includes advanced numbering of nested lists.

4.7:99 The system shall support resetting of braille page numbering at the start of major sections (frontmatter, bodymatter, rearmatter). Resetting numbering for each volume is not part of this requirement.

4.7:100 The system shall be able to perform automatic numbering (i.e. re-numbering) of notes. This feature relies on markup of the original numbering. The numbering shall be resettable for each page or for each volume.

4.7:101 The system shall support resetting braille page numbering for each volume.

4.7:102 The system shall be able to evaluate certain variables and counters at so-called "fields", for example on the title page or in the page header or footer. Supported variables shall include at least the current braille page number, the current print page number or range of print pages contained in the current braille page, the current volume number, the total number of volumes, the total number of braille pages or sheets contained in the current volume or book, the current chapter title, the current chapter number, and the date.

Nota example: if indication of print pagination is enabled, the footer (which appears on recto pages only) will contain the print page or range of print pages covered by the current braille page spread (left/previous + right/current page) 1.

SBS examples: The footer contains the range of print pages, expressed in "downshifted number format".

If only right hand pages have a footer, it's the range of print pages contained in the previous and current braille pages.
If both right and left hand pages have a footer, it's the range of print pages contained in the current braille page.

Explanation:

The footer may appear either on right hand pages only (usually in fiction books) or both on left and right hand pages (in more complex books such as non-fiction or educational literature). (See also requirement 4.5:85.)
The footer contains the range of print page numbers (left-aligned), a short information (heading/cue) about the current section (centered) and the braille page number (right-aligned).
The range of print page numbers is preceded by the symbol _ (dots 456; it's the symbol we generally use to reference print page numbers): _#AB,/ means from print page 12 to print page 14 (the second part of the number ,/ = 14 is a 'downshifted' number format which is also used for dates and ordinal numbers).
If the print page numbers are omitted (or not available), the gap in the footer is filled with ::: (left-aligned) followed immediately by the heading/cue information, e.g. ::: BLABLA #B.
If both print page numbers and heading/cue information is omitted, the text flows into the footer: a gap of at least 2 braille cells is required before the braille page number (right-aligned), e.g. BLA BLA BLA BLA #B. (See also requirement 4.5:83.)

4.7:103 The system shall support insertion of certain variables and counters at references evaluated at the target. An example is references in a table of contents. Supported variables shall include the print page number at the target, the braille page number at the target, and the note number if the target is a renumbered note. This feature relies on explicit markup of references.

4.7:104 The system shall support insertion of certain variables and counters at referenced items evaluated at the reference. Supported variables shall include the volume number at the reference and the braille page number at the reference.

4.7:118 The system shall support the creation of symbols lists, when characters have different meaning than normally (e.g. in mathematics).

Support for indication of original pagination

4.8:105 The system shall provide the possibility of rendering print page breaks as full lines across the width of the page, optionally with the page number of the new print page incorporated in the line. A line break is inserted first whenever a print page break indicator is rendered, and following text continues on the line below the indicator. In other words, the print page break is not taken out of the normal flow of the text in order not to lose precision.

A possible additional requirement is that the print page break may optionally be taken out of the normal text flow:

A page number within a block is extracted such that it appears immediately above the block, again as a line with the number at the end.

issue #36 comment by @stesk

SBS example: Print page breaks are indicated with a full line followed by the page number of the new print page.

Nota example: A page break between paragraphs will appear at its true position as a sequence of dashes followed by the page number. An inline page break is repositioned such that it appears before the parent paragraph, again as the page number preceded by dashes1.

Celia examples: Change of the printed page indicated with a line of 333 and the new print page number.

Example 1
Example 2
Example 3

4.8:106 The system shall provide the possibility of rendering print page breaks as marks in the left margin, taking them out of the normal text flow so that text that follows the element can continue on the same line.

NLB examples:

Rendering print page breaks as marks in the left margin.
Rendering print page breaks as marks in the left margin. The mark is taken out of the normal text flow, and appears at the same line as the word that comes after the pagenum tag.

4.8:107 The system shall support skipping print page breaks when no text precedes or follows on the same braille page.

If print page breaks are not skipped, they should be rendered at the top of a new braille page rather than at the bottom of previous page.

Also, several consecutive print page breaks can be combined into a single break indicator.

SBS example of consecutive print page breaks combined.

Support for ordering and monitoring of braille production

4.9:108 The system shall support templates for different products, e.g. books vs. magazines.

4.9:109 The system shall support templates for different end user groups.

4.9:110 Users shall be able to reuse templates.

4.9:111 Certain users shall be able to create templates.

4.9:112 The system shall save jobs so that e.g. a job history can be showed, and jobs can be rerun.

4.9:113 The user shall be able to monitor jobs: get an overview of the jobs waiting, running, finished, etc., and receive notifications of certain events.

4.9:114 The system shall provide the user with help and guidance for creating templates.

4.9:115 The system shall provide a graphical user interface for creating and monitoring jobs.

Support for mathematics

4.10:119 The system shall support giving marked up mathematics code in ASCII-Math an output according to the mathematical braille code in the Netherlands.

Miscellaneous

4.7:117 The system shall support the possibility to integrate tactile drawings in braille.

Notes

As produced by the current implementation, for demonstration purposes only. Source: https://github.com/stesk/danishbraille.